Guide to the 1964 Mississippi Summer Project Oral Histories, 1994 RL.11814
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
1964 Mississippi Summer Project Oral Histories
1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Biewen, John
Cavett, Kate
Moses, Robert Parris
Blackwell, Unita, 1933-2019
Bryant, Curtis C., 1917-2007
Cobb, Charles E., Jr.
Donaldson, Ivanhoe
Simpson, Euvester, 1945-
Farmer, James, 1920-1999. (Title of work: James Farmer, civil rights leader.)
Guyot, Lawrence, 1939-2012
Hayden, Casey
Head, Rosie M.
Ladner, Dorie
Henry, Aaron, 1922-1997
Lewis, John, 1940 February 21-
McLemore, Leslie Burl
McAdam, Doug
McAuliff, John
Molpus, Dick
Mondale, Walter F., 1928-
O'Neal, John, 1940-
Robinson, Betty Garman
Watkins, Hollis, 1941-
Zellner, Bob
RL.11814
34 items WAV audio files
Thirty-four audio WAV files made from source digital audio tapes of interviews, primarily with participants in the Mississippi Freedom Project, from volunteers to organization leaders.
Arrangement
Interviews are arranged alphabetically by interviewee or title of program.
Biographical / Historical
The Mississippi Freedom Project, also referred to as the Mississippi Summer Project or Freedom Summer, was organized in 1964 by the Council of Federated Organizations, whose member organizations included the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), the Student Non-violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), the National Assocation for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), and the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC). The Project had as a central strategy the recruitment of white college students, many from the North, to help register African American voters in the South while drawing attention of the larger United States to voter suppression based on racial discrimination. The murders of Project volunteers James Chaney, Andrew Goodman, and Michael Schwerner in Mississippi in June galvanized the efforts of Freedom Summer volunteers, whose work helped lead to the Civil Rights Act of 1964 and the Voting Rights Act of 1965.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The 1964 Mississippi Summer Project oral histories were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2020.
Related Materials
Charlie Cobb Interviews, 2012-2013
Joseph A. Sinsheimer Papers, 1962-1987
Larry Rubin Papers, 1961-2010
Center for Documentary Studies, SNCC Legacy Project Critical Oral Histories Conference Interviews, 2016-2018
Collection Overview
Thirty-four audio WAV files made from source digital audio tapes of interviews, primarily with participants in the Mississippi Freedom Project, from volunteers to organization leaders. The recordings were used for a Minnesota Public Radio documentary entitled "O Freedom Over Me," produced by John Biewen and Kate Cavett in 1994. In addition to interviews documenting the Project, Biewen and Cavett also talked to community leaders, educators, and activists regarding conditions for African Americans in Mississippi thirty years after Freedom Summer.
Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Mississippi Freedom Project; Council of Federated Organizations (U.S.); Congress of Racial Equality; Audiovisual materials; Oral histories (document genre); oral histories (literary works); Documentary radio programs; Moses, Robert Parris; Blackwell, Unita, 1933-2019; Bryant, Curtis C., 1917-2007; Cobb, Charles E., Jr.; Donaldson, Ivanhoe; Simpson, Euvester, 1945-; Farmer, James, 1920-1999. (Title of work: James Farmer, civil rights leader.); Guyot, Lawrence, 1939-2012; Hayden, Casey; Head, Rosie M.; Ladner, Dorie; Henry, Aaron, 1922-1997; Lewis, John, 1940 February 21-; McLemore, Leslie Burl; McAdam, Doug; McAuliff, John; Molpus, Dick; Mondale, Walter F., 1928-; O'Neal, John, 1940-; Robinson, Betty Garman; Watkins, Hollis, 1941-; Zellner, Bob
- Interviews, 1994
  Scope and Contents
  In producing their radio documentary in 1994, John Biewen and Kate Cavett used digital audio tape cassettes (DAT), then the cutting edge of portable digital technology. The files in the collection each represent the entirety of a single DAT, and as DAT facilitated high quality and long recording times, many of the files contain more than one interview, along with recordings of ambient sound captured for the production. Interview entries with start and end times provided indicate the interview falls within those times, and that the file includes other interviews or content (listed elsewhere). Those entries with a single time indicate the entire file contains one interview or program.
  - Algebra Project, Indianola, Mississippi, 1994; 01:56:41 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Algebra Project Indianola, MS.wav)
    Includes an interview with Bobby Rushing, principal of Indianola Middle School, Indianola, Mississippi, regarding the Algebra Project, a math education program developed by Bob Moses.
  - Allen, Henry C.; Allen, Mary, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Hank_and_Mary Allen _ MC Campbell.wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:59:00; Hank Allen and Mary Allen, son and daughter of Louis Allen, a black man murdered in 1964 in Liberty, Mississippi for threatening to testify as a witness to the murder of Herbert Lee by state legislator Eugene Hurst.
  - Ash, J.M., 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Smith _ Ash _ Bryant.wav)
    00:27:54 to 01:11:30; J.M. Ash, Marshall County Sheriff
  - Bell Chapel Baptist Church, Sidon, Mississippi, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Mamie Cotton Academy _ Bell Chapel Sidon, MS.wav)
    00:15:41 to 01:49:33; Church meeting and service.
  - Billings, David, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Billings _ O'Neal.wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:46:11; David Billings, Activist, author of Deep Denial.
  - Blackwell, Unita, 1994
    Unita Blackwell, SNCC
    - Part one, 1994; 02:02:32 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Unita Blackwell.wav)
    - Part two, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Unita B _ Rolling Fork Schools.wav)
      00:00:00 to 00:39:50
  - Briggs, Eddie, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Dave Dennis - Eddie Briggs - Mall SFX.wav)
    01:03:40 to 01:21:21; Eddie Briggs, Mississippi Lieutenant Governor, 1992-1996
  - Brown, Ann Gibson, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Brown _ Henry _ Molpus.wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:41:05; Ann Gibson Brown
  - Bryant, C.C., 1994
    C.C. Bryant
    - Part one, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file CC Bryant _ Zellner (1).wav)
      00:00:00 to 00:06:45
    - Part two, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Smith _ Ash _ Bryant.wav)
      01:15:00 to 2:02:43
  - Campbell, M.C., 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Hank_and_Mary Allen _ MC Campbell.wav)
    01:03:15 to 01:26:40; M.C. Campbell, Jr., father of Scott Campbell, who died in police custody in Philadelphia, Mississippi in 1990.
  - Cobb, Charlie; Donaldson, Ivanhoe, 1994; 01:09:20 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Charlie Cobb _ Ivahoe Donaldson.wav)
    Charlie Cobb and Ivanhoe Donaldson, SNCC
  - Cotton, MacArthur; Simpson, Euvester, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Rosie Head _ Euvester Simpson_ Mac Cotton.wav)
    00:57:27 to 01:58:57; MacArthur (Mac) Cotton, SNCC Field Secretary; Euvester Simpson, SNCC and COFO worker.
  - Cotton, Mamie, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Mamie Cotton Academy _ Bell Chapel Sidon, MS.wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:15:40; Mamie Cotton, Southern Echo staff member, discusses the academy system in Mississippi.
  - Dennis, Dave, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Dave Dennis - Eddie Briggs - Mall SFX.wav)
    00:00:00 to 01:02:46; Dave Dennis, COFO, CORE
  - Farmer, James, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file John Lewis _ J Farmer.wav)
    00:49:45 to 01:38:24; James Farmer, National Director of CORE
  - Grayson, Ryan, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Unita B _ Rolling Fork Schools.wav)
    00:41:30 to 01:19:04; Ryan Grayson, Superintendent of South Delta School District, Rolling Fork, Mississippi
  - Guyot, Lawrence, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file McAuliff (2) _ Guyot.wav)
    00:26:48 to 01:30:45; Lawrence Guyot, SNCC
  - Hayden, Casey, 1994
    Casey Hayden, SDS, SNCC
    - Part one, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Mc Adam _ Hayden (1).wav)
      00:41:04 to 01:13:38
    - Part two, 1994; 00:20:58 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Casey Haden (2).wav)
  - Head, Rosie; Washington, Thelma Head, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Rosie Head _ Euvester Simpson_ Mac Cotton.wav)
    00:16:16 to 00:57:26; Rosie Head and Thelma Head Washington, Civil Rights activists in Mississippi
  - Henry, Aaron, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Brown _ Henry _ Molpus.wav)
    00:41:50 to 01:07:10; Aaron Henry, COFO
  - James Chaney family, 1994; 00:56:57 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Chaney Tapes.wav)
    Interview with James Chaney's mother and brother not long after his murder. Source unknown.
  - King, Mary, 1994; 01:49:03 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Mary King.wav)
    Mary King, white SNCC staff worker in the organization's communications department.
  - Ladner, Dorie, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Dorie Ladner _ Betty Garmon Robinson.wav)
    00:00:00 to 01:06:30; Dorie Ladner, SNCC
  - Lewis; John, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file John Lewis _ J Farmer.wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:48:55; John Lewis, SNCC National Chairman
  - Maclemore, Leslie Burt, 1994; 01:22:45 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Leslie Maclemore.wav)
    Leslie Burl McLemore, active with NAACP and SNCC, northern regional coordinator for 1963 Freedom Ballot campaign.
  - McAdam, Doug, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Mc Adam _ Hayden (1).wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:40:00; Doug McAdam, professor of sociology, author, Freedom Summer
  - McAuliff, John, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file McAuliff (2) _ Guyot.wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:25:21; John McAuliff, white Freedom Summer volunteer from Minnesota
  - Molpus, Dick, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Brown _ Henry _ Molpus.wav)
    01:08:08 to 01:48:33; Dick Molpus, Mississippi Secretary of State, 1984-1996
  - Mondale, Walter, 1994; 00:27:06 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Mondale Interview.wav)
    Walter Mondale, Attorney General of Minnesota during 1964, Vice President of the United States, 1977-1981.
  - Morse, Joe, 1994; 01:06:14 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Joe Morse.wav)
    White Freedom Summer volunteer from Minnesota.
  - Moses, Robert, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Watkins-Sayer (2) _ Bob Moses.wav)
    00:00:00 to 01:33:37; Robert Moses, SNCC
  - O'Neal, John, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Billings _ O'Neal.wav)
    00:46:11 to 01:37:00; John O'Neal, SNCC
  - Osman, Robert, 1994; 00:50:37 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Robbie Osman.wav)
    Robert Osman, Freedom Summer volunteer
  - Portera, Theresa, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file West Point Landfill _ Georgiana Podulke.wav)
    00:15:26 to 00:38:34; West Point Landfill, discussion with white resident Theresa Portera regarding placement of landfill in a black community.
  - Robinson, Betty Garmon, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Dorie Ladner _ Betty Garmon Robinson.wav)
    01:06:46 to 02:02:27; Betty Garmon Robinson, SNCC
  - Russell, J.J.; Russell, Erma, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Schools (2) _ Russells.wav)
    00:54:36 to 02:02:24; Reverend J.J. Russell and Erma Russell, Civil Rights activists in Holmes County, Mississippi.
  - Smith, Eddie Lee, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Smith _ Ash _ Bryant.wav)
    00:17:01 to 00:27:53; Eddie Lee Smith, Civil Rights activist, Holly Springs, Mississippi
  - Sound clips from schools, short interviews with educators, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Schools (2) _ Russells.wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:54:35; Discussion of changes in schools, academy schools and white flight.
  - Suarez, Mateo, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Zellner (2) _ Suarez.wav)
    00:23:46 to 01:42:20; Mateo "Flukie" Suarez, CORE
  - Tankson, Katherine; Jackson, Peter, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Unita B _ Rolling Fork Schools.wav)
    01:19:58 to 01:54:37; Katherine Tankson, Director of Curriculum and Instruction, South Delta School District; Peter Jackson, Principal, South Delta High School, Rolling Fork, MS
  - unknown interviewees, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Rosie Head _ Euvester Simpson_ Mac Cotton.wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:16:15; Discussion with elderly black couple regarding the conditions of their farm in Mississippi in the 1950s and 1960s.
  - Watkins, Hollis; Sayer, Michael, 1994; 01:56:11 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Hollis Watkins - M. Sayer (1).wav)
    Hollis Watkins, SNCC Field Secretary and founder of Southern Echo; Michael Sayer, white SNCC staffer in early 1960s.
  - West Point, Mississippi landfill controversy, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file West Point Landfill _ Georgiana Podulke.wav)
    00:00:00 to 00:15:25, 00:38:35 to 00:48:10; West Point Landfill, discussion with a Mr. Brooks, owner of CS's Furniture in West Point Mississippi, regarding placement of landfill in a black community.
  - Zellner, Bob, 1994
    - Part one, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file CC Bryant _ Zellner (1).wav)
      00:09:00 to 02:02:45
    - Part two, 1994 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Zellner (2) _ Suarez.wav)
      00:00:00 to 00:23:45
  - Zimmerman, Dean; Galt, Lester; Oderman, Alvin, 1994; 02:01:35 (Digital-materials SET-0001, Audio-file Galt, Zimmerman.wav)
    Dean Zimmerman, Lester Galt, Alvin Oderman, activists, Freedom Summer volunteers